Steen, Ivan; Papers apap219
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Ivan Steen Papers1936, 1959-2013
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Steen, Ivan D., 1936-
apap219
4.92
The Ivan Steen Papers document Steen's service as a Professor of History at the University at Albany as well as his oral history projects.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of several folders marked below. While Ivan Steen subsequently asked individuals interviewed for the oral history projects he conducted to sign a clearance form or an agreement, not all interview files donated to the archive contain forms. Therefore notes, transcripts and audio of a select number of interviews are restricted until clearance may be obtained from the interviewees or their heirs.
Acquisition Information
Ivan Steen donated his papers to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in a series of acquisitions in 2005, 2007, 2012, 2013, 2015, 2016, and 2017.
Biographical Sketch
Ivan D. Steen was a long time professor at the University at Albany. He began his career at Hunter College of the City University of New York after completing his schooling at New York University, where he received his bachelor’s, master’s, and doctoral degrees. After three years on the faculty at Hunter College, Steen joined the University at Albany's History Department in 1965 as an assistant professor. He became founding director of the University's Public History Graduate Program in 1983, an associate professor in 1985 and associate professor emeritus in 2010. He also served as Vincent O’Leary Associate Professor of History from 2010-2013. During his tenure at the University at Albany, Steen published numerous articles and essays, attended and spoke at academic conferences, lectures, and panels across the country and internationally, and hosted workshops. He was a member of the University Senate as well as a member of United University Professions (UUP). He was elected vice president and president of UUP's Albany chapter during the 1990s and early 2000s. Steen continues to co-direct the Center for Applied Historical Research at the University.
Professor Steen is passionate about oral history and local history. As founding director of the University's Oral History Program, Steen’s projects often focused on a combination of the two. Two of Steen’s major projects were the Erastus Corning Years Oral History Project and The Rockefeller Years: An Oral History of the State of New York Under Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller. Steen, along with students in the program, worked on other projects pertaining to local history such as Albany’s black community, the history of the Fort Orange Club, local area Holocaust survivors, and memories of radio personnel. Steen personally conducted many interviews as did his research associates and students in the Oral History Program. Records of these projects are found in Series 1 along with materials relating to Steen's research of former Prisoners of War (POW) from World War I, World War II, the Korean War, and the Vietnam War.
In 2013 Steen officially retired from his positions at the University at Albany.
Scope and Contents
The Ivan Steen Papers document his work at the University at Albany, including his numerous oral history projects, research conducted for the projects, and his time as an associate professor of History, founding director of the Oral History Program and founding director of the Public History Graduate Program. This collection is divided into two series. The first series, Oral History and Research Files, is arranged alphabetically while the second series, University at Albany History Department, is arranged chronologically.
The Oral History and Research Files series contains audio cassette tapes, transcripts, notes and related correspondence of the interviews conducted by Steen, his colleagues, and his students. Steen's research materials for his multiple oral history projects are housed in this series as well. Researchers should note that material pertaining to the Public History and Oral History Programs are found within the first series, as these programs often produced the work found in said series. Steen’s History Department records, which include memorandum, meeting minutes, correspondence, and reports are retained in Series 2.
Researchers should note that some materials Professor Steen donated were moved to separate collections because he created these records as a member or officer of an organization and not as an individual. Therefore, archivists transferred material pertaining to UUP and the University Senate to their respective collections. Archivists also transferred records to the UUP Oral History Collection. These collections are all found in this department.
For related material, please see the Brothers Records, Daniel Evan Button Papers, Dolores Carrara Papers, Victor A. Lord Papers, Harold Rubin Papers and Malcolm Wilson Papers.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred two monographs: Whispers of Death by Forrest W. Howell and American ex-prisoners of war: non solum armis edited by Gardner Hatch to the book division of Special Collections. These were catalogued and included in Minerva, the University Library Catalog.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 is arranged alphabetically and Series 2 is arranged chronologically.
African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Radio and Television Broadcasting; Military and Armed Conflict; Albany, New York; Oral history--New York (State); Education, Higher--New York (State); New York (State)--Politics and government; Audio cassettes; Interviews; Transcripts; Articles; Memorandums; Steen, Ivan D., 1936-; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; Corning, Erastus, 1909-1983; State University of New York at Albany; New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller)
- Oral History and Research Files, 1936-2013; Undated; 1; 3.72
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1 contains material related to Professor Steen's oral history projects and their related material. Two of his major oral history projects were about Albany Mayor Erastus Corning 2nd and New York Governor Nelson Rockefeller. Other projects pertain to topics such as Albany's black community, the Holocaust, and radio. Please note that formal oral history interviews with prisoners of war were never conducted because grant funding could not be obtained. Folders typically contain correspondence with each interviewee as well as interview transcripts and background information. There are cassette tapes to accompany the interview transcripts. Cassette tapes with general dates or date ranges indicate multiple interview dates.
  - Albany Black Community, Art Mitchell, 1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 1)
  - Albany Black Community, Interview with Art Mitchell, 1984 April 18 (Cassette 1-2)
  - Albany Black Community, Black History in Albany and New York State, 1966; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 2)
  - Albany Black Community, Mrs. Charles Van Vranken, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 3)
  - Albany Black Community, Clarence Parker, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 4)
  - Albany Black Community, Interview with Clarence Parker, 1984 April 30 (Cassette 3-4)
  - Albany Black Community, Interview with Gordon VanNess, Undated (Cassette 170)
  - Albany Black Community, Harriet Gibbons, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 5)
  - Albany Black Community, Interview with Harriet Gibbons, ca. 1984 (Cassette 5)
  - Albany Black Community, Harry Hamilton, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 6)
  - Albany Black Community, Laurence Burwell, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 7)
  - Albany Black Community, Interview with Lawrence Burwell, 1984 May 02 (Cassette 6-8)
  - Albany Black Community, Leon Van Dyke, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 8)
  - Albany Black Community, Interview with Leon Van Dyke, [RESTRICTED], 1984 April 30 (Cassette 9)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
  - Albany Black Community, Michael Nardolillo, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 9)
  - Albany Black Community, Interview with Michael Nardolillo, 1984 April 25 (Cassette 10-11)
  - Albany Black Community, Nell Stokes Holmes, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 10)
  - Albany Black Community, Interview with Nell Stokes Holmes, 1984 May 04 (Cassette 12-13)
  - Albany Black Community, NEH Grant Back Up Materials, 1984; 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 11)
  - Albany Black Community, NEH Grant Correspondence and Material, 1983-1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 12)
  - Albany Black Community, NEH Grant Instructions and Preliminary Application, 1983; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 13)
  - Albany Black Community, Notes, Reception Agenda, Statement of Purpose, 1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 14)
  - Albany Black Community, Reverend Robert Dixon, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 15)
  - Albany Black Community, Interview with Reverend Robert Dixon, [RESTRICTED], 1984 April 19 (Cassette 14-15)
  - Albany Black Community, Interview with Ruby Hughes, 1984 May 16 (Cassette 168)
  - Albany Black Community, Teaching Instructions, Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 16)
  - Albany Democratic Party and Election Results, 1981; 1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 17)
  - Anthony Metzner Memoirs, Correspondence, Forms, and Transcripts, 1985; 1995 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 18)
  - Interviews with Anthony Metzner, 1983 (Cassette 16-17)
  - Articles about O'Connell and the Political Machine, 1967; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 19-20)
  - Button and Herzog Primary Race, News Articles, 1966 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 21)
  - Collins, Evan R. Collins Interview, [RESTRICTED], 1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 22)
  - Collins, Interview with Evan R. Collins, [RESTRICTED], 1984 March 19 (Cassette 36)
  - Corning, Arnold Proskin Interview, Correspondence, and Background Information, 1986-1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 23)
  - Corning, Interview with Arnold Proskin, 1984 January 26 (Cassette 20-21)
  - Corning, Bishop Howard Hubbard Interview and Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 24)
  - Corning, Interview with Bishop Howard Hubbard, 1987 November 10 (Cassette 22-23)
  - Corning, Comments on P. Grondahl's Mayor Erastus Corning, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 25)
  - Corning, Daniel Button Interviews, 1983-1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 26-27)
  - Corning, Interviews with Daniel Button, 1983-1984 (Cassette 24-32)
  - Corning, Death and Project Review, 1983; 1985; 1999; 2003 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 28)
  - Corning, Dorothea Noonan Correspondence and Articles, 1987; 1995; 2005 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 29)
  - Corning, Douglas Brown Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 30)
  - Corning, Erastus Corning Assembly Biography, 1936 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 31)
  - Corning, Erastus Corning 2nd, Articles, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 32)
  - Corning, Erastus Corning 2nd, Interview, Tape Indexes, Correspondence and Background Information, 1982-1987 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 33)
  - Corning, Interview with Erastus Corning 2nd, August 11 1982 (Cassette 33-34)
  - Corning, The Erastus Corning Years Oral History Project, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 34)
  - Corning, Erastus Corning 2nd: Seminars in Local History, Albany Institute of History and Art, 1979 December 08 (Cassette 35)
  - Corning, Francis Bergan, Correspondence and Interview, 1983-1991; 1993; 1998; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 35-36)
  - Corning, Interviews with Francis Bergan, 1984-1989 (Cassette 37-49)
  - Corning, Harold Rubin Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 37)
  - Corning, Harold Segal Interviews, 1987-1990 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 38)
  - Corning, Interviews with Harold Segal, 1987-1988 (Cassette 50-57)
  - Corning, Human Subject Review, 1982-1999; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 39)
  - Corning, Information about the Project and Interviews Conducted, Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 40)
  - Corning, James Gallagher Interview, 1984; 1988 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 41)
  - Corning, Interviews with James Gallagher, 1984-1985 (Cassette 58-66)
  - Corning, James T. Foley Interview, Correspondence, and Articles, 1986-1988; 1990; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 42)
  - Corning, Interviews with James T. Foley, 1986-1987 (Cassette 67-70)
  - Corning, John Cross Interview, [RESTRICTED], 1984 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 43)
  - Corning, Interview with John Cross, [RESTRICTED], 1984 March 15 (Cassette 71)
  - Corning, Joseph Yavoditte, Correspondence with his Family, 1982 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 44)
  - Corning, Lewis Swyer Correspondence and Newsclippings, 1981-1988 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 45)
  - Corning, Michael Bergan Correspondence about Francis Bergan Interviews, 2012 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 46)
  - Corning, Newspaper Clippings for the Project, 1982-1987 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 47)
  - Corning, Project Background Information, 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 48)
  - Corning, Richard Conners Interviews, Articles, and Correspondence, 1960; 1966; 1983-1995 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 49)
  - Corning, Interviews with Richard Conners, 1986-1987 (Cassette 72-76)
  - Corning, William Hennessy Correspondence, Article, and "Hats Off Dinner", 1983; 1985; 1987 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 50)
  - Corning, William Thompson Jr. Interview and Correspondence, 1990; 1992 (Box 1 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 51)
  - Corning, Interview with William Thompson Jr., 1990 October 10 (Cassette 77-78)
  - Corning and Rockefeller, Joseph McGovern Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 1)
  - Daniel Button, Articles, 1966-1968 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 2)
  - Democratic State Committee, 1936 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 3)
  - The Downfall of the Barnes Machine, Student Paper, 1969 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 4)
  - File from Rockefeller Cabinet Member Neal Moylan, 1968-1974 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 5)
  - Fort Orange, Correspondence, Human Subject Review and Agreement, 1992-1993 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 6)
  - General W. Reynolds Carr Interview, 1992-1993 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 7)
  - Interviews with General W. Reynolds Carr, 1993 (Cassette 79-82)
  - George Harder, Interviews and Background Information, 1961-1967; 1983-1984; Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 8-9)
  - Interviews with George Harder, 1984 (Cassette 83-91)
  - Harold Koreman Background Information, Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 10)
  - History Lives! Conference Program, 2013 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 11)
  - History of the Albany Common Council Project, Nancy Burton and Stephen McArdle Jr, 1999 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 12)
  - Holocaust Project, Article, Background Information, Notes, and Interview Transcripts, [RESTRICTED], 1978; 1983; Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 13)
  - Holocaust Project, Correspondence, Human Subject Review, [RESTRICTED], 1983-1984; Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 14)
  - Holocaust Project, Interviews with Imac Metzger, [RESTRICTED], 1984 (Cassette 92-93)
  - Holocaust Project, Interviews with Lila Klein, [RESTRICTED], 1983 (Cassette 94-99)
  - Holocaust Project, Interviews with Murray Jaros, 1983 (Cassette 100-103)
  - Map of New York State Showing Number of Members of Assembly, 1936 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 15)
  - Map of New York State Showing Senatorial Districts, 1936 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 16)
  - Memoir of Colonel Armand Hobins, 1982; 1988 (Oversized 1)
  - Michael McNulty Background Information, Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 17)
  - The Monaghen Investigation, Student Paper, 1967 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 18)
  - New York State Assembly Members, 1936 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 19)
  - The New York Crystal Palace Exhibition, Steen's Master's Thesis, 1959 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 20)
  - New York State Joint Legislative Committee, 1936 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 21)
  - Oral History Program, Correspondence, 1982-1983; 1993; 1996 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 22)
  - Oral History Program, Fundraising, 1982-1986 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 23)
  - Oral History Program, Project Proposals, 1984; 1995 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 24)
  - POW, A Modern Day Tragedy, 1980 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 25)
  - POW, American Ex-POWs Inc. Information, 1985; Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 26)
  - POW, American Ex-POWs Inc. National Medial Research Committee Packets 8-10, 1980-1981 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 27)
  - POW, Correspondence and Newsclippings, 1987-1991 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 28)
  - POW Courage Personified by Lysle Lewis, ca. 1988 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 29)
  - POW, "Death March" Article, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 30)
  - POW, History of Baatan Relief Organization, Bataan Veterans Organization, and History of American Ex-POW, 1972-1989 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 31)
  - POW, Japan and World War II POWs, Newsclippings, and Memoirs, John Browe, and Far East POWs, 1971; 1975; 1987-1988; Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 32)
  - POW, Prisoners of War Bibliography, 1985; Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 33)
  - POW Prisoners of War by W.P. Skelton, 1988; Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 34)
  - POW Sandy: Death March Survivor and Search for Truth by Lysle Lewis, Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 35)
  - POW, 42nd Annual National Convention of American Ex-POWs Program, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 36)
  - Proctor's Theatre, Correspondence, 1991 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 37)
  - Public History, Affirmative Action Grant Proposal, 1991-1994 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 38)
  - Public History and Public Memory Pamphlet, 1997 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 39)
  - Public History Perspectives Newsletter, 2002-2009 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 40)
  - Public History Program Brochures, Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 41)
  - Radio, Dolores Carrara Interview, 2004-2005 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 42)
  - Radio, Interview with Dolores Carrara, 2004 November 11 (Cassette 103-104)
  - Radio, Edward Dahlstedt Interview, 2004 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 43)
  - Radio, Interview with Edward Dahlstedt, 2004 July 29 (Cassette 105-106)
  - Radio, Jack Hotchkiss Interview, [RESTRICTED], 2005-2006 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 44)
  - Radio, Interview with Jack Hotchkiss, [RESTRICTED], 2005 April 11 (Cassette 107)
  - Radio, Louise Marshall Interview, 2005 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 45)
  - Radio, Interview with Louise Marshall, 2004 November 11 (Cassette 108-109)
  - Radio, Margaret Miller Interview, 2004 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 46)
  - Radio, Interview with Margaret Miller, 2004 May 24 (Cassette 110)
  - Ralph Ciccarelli Interview, [RESTRICTED], 1981 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 47)
  - Interview with Ralph Ciccarelli, [RESTRICTED], ca. 1981 (Cassette 111-112)
  - Record of 1936 Legislature (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 48)
  - Rena Button Interview, [RESTRICTED], 1984 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 49)
  - Interview with Rena Button, RESTRICT, 1984 February 29 (Cassette 113)
  - Rockefeller, Alton Marshall Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 50)
  - Rockefeller, Correspondence, 1982-1983; Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 51)
  - Rockefeller, Daniel Dalrymple, Interviews, Memoir, Correspondence, and Notes, 1982-1984; Undated (Box 2 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 52-53)
  - Rockefeller, Daniel Dalrymple, Interviews, Memoir, Correspondence, and Notes, 1982-1984; Undated (Box 3 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 1-2)
  - Rockefeller, Interviews with Daniel Dalrymple, 1983 (Cassette 114-123)
  - Rockefeller, Edward Logue, Interviews and Correspondence, 1983-1993 (Box 3 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 3-7)
  - Rockefeller, Interviews with Edward Logue, 1983-1991 (Cassette 124-145)
  - Rockefeller, Former Governor Malcolm Wilson Interviews, Notes, and Correspondence, 1982-1984; 1989; Undated (Box 4 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 1-2)
  - Rockefeller, Interviews with Former Governor Malcolm Wilson, 1983/1984 (Cassette 146-157)
  - Rockefeller, Human Subject Review, 1982-1992 (Box 4 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 3)
  - Rockefeller, Joseph Swidler, [RESTRICTED], 1982-1983 (Box 4 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 4)
  - Rockefeller, Interview with Joseph Swidler, [RESTRICTED], 1982 December 11 (Cassette 158-159)
  - Rockefeller, Neil Moylan Interview, Correspondence, and Notes, 1982-1984; Undated (Box 4 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 5)
  - Rockefeller, Interviews with Neil Moylan, 1984 (Cassette 160-163)
  - Rockefeller, Project Background Materials, 1968; 1976; 1983; Undated (Box 4 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 6)
  - Rockefeller, Robert Helsby Correspondence and Interview, 1982-1984 (Box 4 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 7)
  - Rockefeller, Interview with Robert Helsby, 1982 December 11 (Cassette 164-165)
  - Rockefeller, Robert McManus Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 4 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 8)
  - Rockefeller, "Rockefeller in Retrospect" Conference, 1982 December 10-1982 December 11 (Box 4 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 9)
  - Ronald Grele, Correspondence about Consulting, 1982-1983 (Box 4 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 10)
  - Siena College, Fr. Ben Kuhn Interview, 1987 (Box 4 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 11)
  - South End Scene, 1984; Undated (Flat-file 1)
  - "A Strategic Plan for the New York State Museum" and Correspondence, 1991 (Box 4 (1-Oral History and Research Files), Folder 12)